<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Habakkuks prayer applyed to the churches present occasions, on Hab. 3. 2. And Christs counsel to the church of Philadelphia, on Rev. 3. 11. / Preached before the provincial assembly of London. By that late reverend and faithful minister of Jesus Christ Mr. Samuel Balmford, pastor of Albons Woodstreet.</title>
            <author>Balmford, Samuel, d. 1659?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1910_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209972</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868816</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868816</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154431</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77987)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154431)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 237:E1910[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Habakkuks prayer applyed to the churches present occasions, on Hab. 3. 2. And Christs counsel to the church of Philadelphia, on Rev. 3. 11. / Preached before the provincial assembly of London. By that late reverend and faithful minister of Jesus Christ Mr. Samuel Balmford, pastor of Albons Woodstreet.</title>
                  <author>Balmford, Samuel, d. 1659?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 109, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.M. for Adroniram Byfield at the three Bibles in Corn-hil neer Popeshead-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Habakkuk III, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation III, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154431:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>HABAKK<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KS</hi> PRAYER Applyed to the Churches preſent occaſions, on <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 2.</p>
            <p>AND <hi>CHRISTS</hi> COUNSEL To the Church of <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia,</hi> on <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
            <p>Preached before the Provincial Aſſembly of <hi>London.</hi> By that late Reverend and faithful Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt Mr. SAMUEL BALMFORD, Paſtor of Albons <hi>Woodſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 30. 7.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alas, for that day is great, ſo that none is like it; It is even the time of Jacobs trouble. But he ſhall be ſaved out of it.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>Adoniram Byfield</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Corn-hil</hi> neer <hi>Popeſhead-Alley.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:154431:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154431:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Judicious</hi> READER,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſuch the works of this holy man of God Mr. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Balmford</hi> (now with the Lord) require and deſerve: Here is repreſented to thee a Forlorn-hope, or two Scouts, being a ſmall parcel of thoſe many excellent pieces intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:154431:3"/> for the preſſe; ſent before <hi>ad vada tentanda,</hi> not as if theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were of higher ſtature in worth then others their fellows, and therefore fitter for it: Among all Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatives, Compariſons are excluded: <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Zara</hi> ſtrove with equal ſtrength for precedency of birth; but this piece to ſatisfie the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of friends hath broken forth firſt. The Author was a perſon of eminent Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy of Word and Life, by both which, as a burning and ſhining light, he was an exact and powerful Teacher; the obſervant eye of impartial converſers with him finding
<pb facs="tcp:154431:3"/> the Tranſcript of his Sermons in his life, his actions being living, walking Sermons. He was a man of a meek and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſpirit, cloathed with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; lowly in heart, but high and eminent for gifts and graces in the eſteem when li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and honoring remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance now dead, of thoſe that are beſt able to judge of real worth. An excellent husbander of time, a painfull Student, of great diligence and faithfulneſſe in all Truſts and Relations, of much Candor, affability, communicativeneſs, and condeſcention in matters capable of it, but immoveable where ſence of duty obliged
<pb facs="tcp:154431:4"/> him. Not forward to ſpeak, and therefore his words were more ſavoury by lying long in the falt of a delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate minde, and adminiſtring more grace to the hearers. A man of a publick ſpirit, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying ſouls, mourning for the ſins of others, and deeply lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to heart the afflictions of the people of God abroad, and their diſſentions at home, as theſe enſuing Sermons do abundantly teſtifie. For his labours in the Miniſtry, he was one would not do the work of the Lord negligently, nor offer unto God what coſt him nothing, or a corrupt thing, when as indeed he (if
<pb facs="tcp:154431:4"/> any) had a male in the flock, and was a workman that need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not be aſhamed. He thought the delivery of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies from God to man, moſt needed and beſt deſerved care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful preparation, and therefore choſe rather to approve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his Maſter, and the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſmaller number of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious hearers by an induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſearching the Scriptures, and digging to the bottome of that excellent Mine, than to ſpare himſelf and pleaſe the moſt by taking up with the neareſt, uppermoſt, and leſſe precious parcels of Ore: he hung not forth Alchimy lace that a little wearing by judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:154431:5"/> meditation would have changed the colour of, but of ſuch true and pure metal as would wear brighter and brighter. When ſome tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row injudiciouſneſſe and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly prejudice (the Lord give ſuch repentance to life) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted his bodily preſence, (as they <hi>Pauls)</hi> weak and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, and felt not the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and demonſtration of the ſpirit in his words, others more judicious and candid hearers, Chriſtians and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have had their ſouls hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his lips, and heard him with joy and delight to their great profiting. Though he well knew the diſtempered
<pb facs="tcp:154431:5"/> palate of theſe diſeaſed times, yet would not this fiſher of men bait the ground to draw multitudes about him with curious enquiries and ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, unprofitable though pleaſing notions, <hi>quarum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventarum ſolus fructus eſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniſſe)</hi> nor talking imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencies without book, or fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling up vacuities by moſt inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid and nauſeous tautologies. He did not by ſtrength and ſtrain of lungs, comick actions, peculiar modes of carriage, (having more of affectation than affection in them) make up defect of matter, nor cloud wiſdom with words without knowledge, wrapping up my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious
<pb facs="tcp:154431:6"/> non-ſenſe in ſilken phraſes, nor dreſſe up ſober truths in the meretricious garb of enticing words of mans wiſdom: nor yet did he proſtitute the Word to the contempt of the worldly-wiſe, or diſadvantage it to better-minded, more judicious hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by flatneſſe or rudeneſſe of ſtile, but ſought out accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table words, thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> making words ſtill ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to matter, neither going before vainly, nor yet follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at too great a diſtance neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently. He did not leap into his matter without trying and ſhowing the ground he went upon, but accurately weighed
<pb facs="tcp:154431:6"/> the Original, carefully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with expoſitors, ſolid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtated the ſubject of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and then excellently divided the Word of Truth by exact natural Method, and faithful application to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent conditions of ſoules, therein not venting his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor concealing Gods truth. He was every way ſuch, as not to have known him was an unhappineſſe; to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed known him and not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured him, an impoſſibility: Of him the world was not worthy, he therefore is taken away from the evil to come.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I freely teſtify from the full knowledge I had
<pb facs="tcp:154431:7"/> of him, having by him been allowed the happineſſe of a free converſe and intimate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him, by which I muſt acknowledge my ſelfe to have been much and often profited.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Parſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="endorsement">
            <pb facs="tcp:154431:7"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Reverend and Learned <hi>Author</hi> of theſe enſuing Sermons, (very ſeaſonable and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for theſe times) was a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt</hi> endued with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good abilities, a <hi>workman that needed not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, rightly dividing the word of truth;</hi> full of <hi>piety, modeſty, humility,</hi> and <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity;</hi> Sound in the <hi>Faith,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable in the <hi>Truth,</hi> painful in his <hi>Miniſterial imployment,</hi> and one who hath left a <hi>precious</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:154431:8"/> 
               <hi>name</hi> behind him among ſtall thoſe who throughly knew him. And therefore unto the teſtimony gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of him by my <hi>Reverend Brother,</hi> I do freely, chearfully, and moſt heartily ſubſcribe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 1. in the Text, for receive, <hi>r.</hi> revive, for people <hi>r.</hi> years, p. 2. l. 21. for open <hi>r.</hi> opine, p. 5. l. 15. <hi>dele</hi> and mercy, page 6. line 9. for uſe <hi>r.</hi> verſe, page 13. line 10. for Pſal. <hi>r.</hi> Iſai. p. 15. l. 4. for favor <hi>r.</hi> wrath, p. 34. l. 21. for know <hi>r.</hi> known, p. 41. l. 2. <hi>dele</hi> experienced and appeared, p. 53. l. 4. for of <hi>r.</hi> by, p. 66. l. 26. for keep <hi>r.</hi> kept, p. 72. l. 11. for Chriſt <hi>r.</hi> Christians, p. 78. l. 8. for uſual <hi>r.</hi> uſeful, p. 84. l. 9. for apprehenſion <hi>r.</hi> approach.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154431:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Habakkuks</hi> Prayer apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Churches preſent occaſions.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Habakkuk 3. 2.</bibl>
               <q>O Lord, I have heard thy ſpeech, and was afraid: O Lord, receive thy work in the midſt of thy people, in the midſt of the year make known: in wrath remember mercy.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Propheſie of this holy Prophet is term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>Burden,</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in regard of the ſad and heavy threatnings and curſes which are denounced againſt ſeveral ſorts of perſons in it. When it was that he ſaw this burden, that is, when he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154431:9"/> received it from the Lord in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick-Viſion, or when he held it forth to be ſeen of the people of God, by a Prophetick publication, is not preciſely certain; No doubt it was not long before the captivity of the <hi>Jews</hi> by the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> and ſo either in, or after the raign of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> but more probably a good while after it, than under it; yea to me it ſeems not improbable that it was about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> reign, after the <note place="margin">So <hi>Danae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
               </note> Jews had taſted ſomewhat of the bitterneſs and haſtineſs of the <hi>Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in carrying away <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Babylon,</hi> though they had not yet gone through the breadths of the Land, nor compleated the captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as they did, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years after. But let this be left indifferent to the Learned to open at pleaſure.</p>
            <p>The Contents of this Book are held forth mainly in three parcels, according to the diviſion of it into three Chapters.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154431:9"/>
            <p> In the firſt we finde the ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Jews, (their perverſe diſobediences and preſent impunity ſeeming burdenous to the Prophet himſelf:) (the people of God at that time, though much degenerated) laid down partly by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint made to God, partly by way of menacing from God, that he would in a ſtrange manner bring them under the power of the <hi>Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> And then, upon the Prophets Deprecation that God would not utterly deſtroy his people, but cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe them in meaſure, eſpecially, ſince he took thoſe whom God was about to make as the rod in his hand, and the inſtrument of ſcourging, to be worſe then they who were to be ſcourged.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Chapter, after the Prophets profeſſed <hi>ſtanding upon his watch to hear what the Lord will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him,</hi> we finde he had an anſwer by way of <hi>viſion,</hi> tending to the comfort of Gods people, but ſuch as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154431:10"/> they were to <hi>wait for till the appointed time</hi> that the viſion was to ſpeak, that is, till it ſhould be manifeſted effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually; For all that are <hi>juſt</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right before God are to <hi>live by faith,</hi> and that faith to ſhew it ſelf in a wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tarrying patience. And that excellent Principle, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by faith,</hi> we may finde three times alledged in the New Teſtament, <hi>viz. Rom.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 38.</p>
            <p>Now the Contents of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Viſion, concerned the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall and ruine of the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> the wicked enemies of Gods people, and that for their unſatiable pride, and ambition, and covetouſneſs, and cruelty, and drunkenneſs, and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. But beloved, God looks to be ſought unto for the fulfilling of all his praedictions in behalf of his Church and people. Therefore</p>
            <p>In this third Chapter we finde the holy Prophet framing a <hi>Prayer</hi> in the behalf of the Church, and for the uſe of the Church doubtleſs in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154431:10"/> And accordingly <hi>Luther</hi> notes it as a Prayer or Song (for it is metrical in the Hebrew, and ſet for Muſical Inſtruments) which hath been <hi>[in quotidiano uſu per omnia paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim templa]</hi> in daily uſe almoſt in all Churches; though (ſaith he) moſt commonly as Nunns read the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without underſtanding. Now the Contents of this Prayer lies ſummarily in Petitions concerning the Church of God, and in grounds of thoſe Petitions, taken chiefly from former demonſtrations of Gods power and mercy, and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his Church, and in profeſſed confidences and rejoycings upon thoſe aſſuring grounds. Therefore</p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſpend time in a punctual Analyſis of it, nor ſpeak any thing of the <hi>Inſcription</hi> of it in the firſt verſe; only, this we may note, that as it was ſet or compoſed according to variable tunes in the Hebrew cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Shigionoth</hi> (as our Learned Tranſlators gloſs it) ſo may it be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154431:11"/> made uſe of on various occaſions by Gods people. And as this Prophet ſealed up the Doctrine of the life of Faith in this Prayer by the exerciſe and demonſtration of it, ſo ſhould we do in making any accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it unto the Churches preſent occaſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> This ſecond Uſe which I have taken for my preſent ſubject matter to treat of, holds forth the grand requeſt of the Prophet, and which he moſt intended in this Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that indeed which all that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in it referrs unto, either in the nature of argument that it ſhould be granted, or of conſequent upon the ſuppoſed grant of it. The whole verſe contains</p>
            <p n="1">1. A preparative of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear in the way of addreſs to God, <hi>[O Lord, I have heard thy ſpeech, and was afraid,]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Prayer of Faith; and this Prayer brancheth it ſelf into two or three Petitions.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154431:11"/>
               <item>1. <hi>O Lord, revive thy work in the midſt of the years;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. In the midſt of the years make known.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>In wrath remember mercy.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Petitions that are of near affinity one to the other, and full of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis in the expreſſions: For the firſt is the chief and primary; The ſecond may be taken to be but an enforcement of the firſt, by a Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical Anadiploſis or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> taking up again theſe terms <hi>[In the midſt of the years]</hi> and adding only <hi>[make known]</hi> ſomewhat abruptly, yet ſo as by an eaſie reference we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his meaning to be, Make known thy reviving, or revived work; And the third implies the ſame thing; only involves an Argument from the nature of God, to urge the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, as we may hear in the Sequel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> Begin we with the Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Fear. <hi>[O Lord, I have head thy ſpeech, and was afraid.]</hi> What
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154431:12"/> ſpeech means he? Not the ſpeech, or fame, or report that is of thee, (though the Original word <hi>Sual</hi> ſo ſignifies) but the ſpeech that hath been ſpoken by thee; And that as partly concerning the Calamities thou haſt threatned to bring upon the Jews, and partly concerning the deſtruction thou haſt threatned to the Chaldeans: And hearing this, <hi>I was afraid;</hi> What? (you may ſay) afraid of the judgements of God denounced againſt the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the enemies of the people of God? Its even of them, <hi>Ne Judae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os etiam in Babylone captivos involvat clades Chaldaeorum &amp; omnino deleat,</hi> (ſaith <hi>A Lapide)</hi> Leſt the Iews alſo ſhould be wrapped in the ſame bundle of deſtruction with the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans, being found reſident among them, and ſo be utterly ruined together with them. Now touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Fear, after what manner he was affected, we may gather by what was ſaid after at verſe 16.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154431:12"/> where he makes recognition of his temper before he had prayed, and gathered ſtrength and confidence upon the remembrance of Gods wonderful workings. <hi>Therefore when I heard, (lo) my belly trembled, my lips qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered at the voice, rottenneſs entred into my bones.</hi> The paſſions he was ſtruck into were very great, and the trouble of his Spirit, and the Symptomes of it upon him were very terrible, though all tending to good, &amp;c. Well,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> We have here to obſerve, that The beſt of Gods ſervants are, and ought to be affected with fear and trembling at the denunciation of Gods judgements, and eſpecially at the Prognoſticks and ſignals of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and miſeries hanging over the Church and people of God. <hi>My fleſh trembleth for fear of thee, and I am afraid of thy judgements;</hi> ſo <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Pſal. 119. 120. Good King <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> having certain intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of grear Forces of combined Enemies preparing againſt him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154431:13"/> Gods people, <hi>he feared,</hi> 2 Chr. 20. 3. <hi>And Jehoſhaphat feared, and ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſeek the Lord, and proclaimed a faſt throughout all Judah.</hi> And ſuch a feare well tempered ought to be found in them, upon ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and that moſt rationally; For conſider with me, I beſeech you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſpeech, and voice of God when it is but preceptive onely, and in the way of commanding, is enough to ſtrike his people with fear, as it may be preſented to them in a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick manner; So it did at <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> when God delivered his Law to his people, though then they ſtood upon good terms with him; For there is a dreadfulneſs ever in the Soveraign Majeſtique Preſence of God. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 7. <hi>God is greatly to be feared in the aſſembly of the Saints, and to be had in reverence of all them that are about him.</hi> Much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then when he utters himſelf in the way of threatnings of judgments, which are moſt fit to beget fears in the ſoul.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:154431:13"/> 2. We know that the very good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, and his pardoning mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſhould work the ſoul about by the way of love unto a Reverential and Cautionary Fear of offending him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 4. <hi>But there is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs with thee, that thou mayeſt be feared.</hi> How much more properly then may the ſeverity of God, and his menaced judgements cauſe a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling fear in them whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern?</p>
            <p n="3">3. We finde God offended at men, and thoſe of his own people, not only for formal ſinfull matters of provocation, but even for not fearing as they ſhould, and not trembling before him in the way of his judgements. So with <hi>Judah;</hi> I <hi>ſaw</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when for all the cauſes whereby backſliding Iſrael committed adultery, I had put her away, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven her a bill of divorce, yet her treacherous ſiſter</hi> Judah <hi>feared not, &amp;c.</hi> Jer. 3. 8. So with the remnant of <hi>Judah</hi> during the Captivity in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:154431:14"/> who went down into <hi>Egypt;</hi> For God threatned them for having forgotten the wickedneſs of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for not being humbled at that day, nor having feared, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 44. 9, 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And on the contrary we finde God in a juſt expectal of this fearfull trembling diſpoſition at the voice of his threatnings and judgements, and well pleaſed with it; <hi>The Lion hath roared, who will not fear?</hi> Amos 3. 8. <hi>Shall a Trumpet be blown in the City, and the people not be afraid?</hi> Jude ver. 6. <hi>To this man will I look, ſaith God, even to him that is poore, and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my word,</hi> Iſa. 66. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what manner of fear and trembling at Gods threatnings may this be which is required? Doth not the Scripture ſay that <hi>The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man ſhall not be afraid of evill tidings, becauſe his heart is fixed, truſting in the Lord?</hi> Pſal. 112. 7. And doth not the Scripture divers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154431:14"/> times forbid, and reprove the people of God for their fear of enemies, and oppreſſors, and a ſad, and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous condition under them? Who <hi>art thou</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>that art afraid of a man that ſhall dye, and of the ſon of man that ſhall be made as graſs, &amp;c?</hi> and that haſt <hi>feared continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the fury of the oppreſſor,</hi> as if he were ready to deſtroy, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It muſt be granted there is a great deale of fear that the poor people of God are ſubject unto in this life, which is, and may moſt juſtly be interdicted, and forbidden to them, and checked in them by the Spirit of God, as being inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate, and ſinfull in ſundry reſpects; and yet it muſt be held that there is a fear of threatned judgements from God, which is not onely indulged to them, but falls under duty. There is a great deale of baſe ſlaviſh fear in the ground of it, &amp; of exceſſive fear in the degree of it, and of either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154431:15"/> or otherwiſe unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fear in the time of it, as it then works unſeaſonably when God after a time of long publick triall, and affliction, diſcovers himſelf by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry tokens, and evidences ready to comfort his people. And ſo in that place mentioned in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51, 12, 13. [See the Context thereabout] But while God ſpeaks terrible things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his his people, they ought to fear; Provided that their feare be thus qualified.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be a Fear that hath the great God properly for its Object, and not the Creature. I take it to be generally obſervable in the holy Scripture, that God finds not fault with his people, or any other for fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him; no, not meerly in regard of his power and wrath, as King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; See <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 7. <hi>Who would not fear thee, O King of Nations? for to thee doth it appertain: foraſmuch as among all the wiſe men of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and in all their Kingdoms, there</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154431:15"/> 
               <hi>is none like unto thee.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 11. <hi>Who knoweth the power of thine anger? even according to thy fear, ſo is thy favour.</hi> Iſa. 19. 16. <hi>In that day ſhall Egypt be like unto women: and it ſhall be afraid and fear becauſe of the ſhaking of the hand of the Lord of Hoſts, which he ſhaketh over it.</hi> But for fearing the Creature, ſuppoſe the inſtrument he uſeth of his wrath, or puniſhing diſpleaſure, is that werein the baſe degeneration of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane fear lieth, that men look not at, or conſider not the chief Efficient and Meritorious cauſes of judgment threatned, but the matter of it, &amp; the Inſtruments of it only; And ſo, not at the hand of God in it, and his diſpleaſure ſtirred up by ſin, but at the hand of man, or other Creatures executing it, and the matter of loſs or ſmart in it; Their fear is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Name of God <hi>(Mal.</hi> 2. 5.) but before the names and faces of men. Now this is baſe, and quite contrary to the temper that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154431:16"/> who in caſe of judgements, or dangers, would not have ſenſual, but ſpiritual conſiderations taken on; for they that know Gods Name aright, ſhould learn (by an holy Chimiſtry, as it were) to abſtract a ſpirituall fear of the Creator from the carnall feare of Creatures, and preſerve that fear by them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be a Fear that riſeth not onely out of Self-love, as appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive only of perſonal dangers: But a fear that ariſeth from true bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly charity born towards the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of Gods People, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of Divine anger kindled againſt them, and of dangers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them. This Prophet feared in the behalf of the people, and prayed in behalf of the people of God, and not of himſelf, either only, or chiefly. Publique reſpects ſhould outweigh private, in all that would be accepted of God in their addreſſes to him. Yea indeed the regard of the publique Intereſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154431:16"/> ſhould ſwallow up the regard of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſt in all thoſe that would finde good acceptance with God; as it did in <hi>Moſes</hi> when God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. See <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 9. <hi>&amp;c. And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>I have ſeen this people, and behold, it is a ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked people.</hi> Deut. 9. 18, 19. &amp;c. <hi>And I fell down before the Lord, as at the firſt forty daies and forty nights; I did neither eat bread, nor drink water, becauſe of all your ſins which ye ſinned, in doing wickedly in the ſight of the Lord, to provoke him to anger. (For I was afraid of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and hot diſpleaſure wherewith the Lord was wroth againſt you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy you.) But the Lord hearkened un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me at that time alſo.</hi> And in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> 2 Sam. 24. 17. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>ſpake unto the Lord when he ſaw the Angel that ſmote the people, and ſaid, Loe; I have ſinned, and I have done wickedly: but theſe ſheep, what have they done? Let thine hand, I pray thee, be againſt me, and againſt my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154431:17"/> 
               <hi>houſe.</hi> For affection toward Gods people may be ſuppoſed as wrapping under it ſome reſpect alſo to the Name and Honour of God, leſt it ſhould ſuffer in their ruine and deſtruction; [Note for this ſome of <hi>Moſes</hi> his expreſſions, &amp;c.]</p>
            <p n="3">3. It muſt be a Fear that is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled as well at the ſins which are the cauſes of Gods threatnings, as at the threatnings themſelves, and ſo it muſt be a holy Fear, as was this Prophets, witneſs the beginning of his Propheſie. For as the ſting of death is ſin, ſo the ſting of every pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and affliction is ſin to ſuch as have a right feeling.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It muſt be a Fear that doth not drive away from God, but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the party poſſeſſed with it to God; Not a fear fil'd with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and deſpair, but with hope of Divine mercy. And ſo, not a fear according to the ſtamp of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> who, when he had ſinned, <hi>hearing the voice of the Lord in the</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:154431:17"/> 
               <hi>Garden was afraid, and hid himſelf,</hi> (Gen. 3. 19.) but a fear well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming the followers of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> Principled in Faith, and ſo inclining to ſeek to God by Prayer; as knowing there is no way to flee from God, but to God; from his wrath, but to his mercy. And this operation we find here this fear had in the Prophet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> All the uſe of this Point that I commend unto you, Beloved, ſhall be by way of Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To conſider if we have not at this day ſuch a voice or ſpeech of God in our ears as may make us afraid. True; we have no ſuch Prophets among us as <hi>Habakkuk</hi> (for ought I know) to ſee burdens in way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Viſion, and to declare them; But, know we that God threatens really as well as verbally, and menaces may be gathered from his Providences as well as from his Propheſies; And thoſe ſad threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which are denounced primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154431:18"/> and directly but to one Nation, or People, are appliable in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, to other Nations or People of like condition for guiltineſs. Briefly then take we a review whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought of the Prophets ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to God, or of Gods ſpeech by him be applicable to the people we relate unto, that we may perceive whether we have cauſe to be afraid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Look we into the firſt complaint of the Prophet touching the ſins of the people He complaines that <hi>ſpoiling and violence are before him,</hi> and there are that <hi>raiſe up ſtrife and contention</hi> (Chap. 1. 3.) <hi>that the Law is ſlacked, and judgement goeth not forth, but wrong judgement proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> verſe 4. And is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of like complaint that may be made among us?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Look next unto the threatned ſad condition of the <hi>Jews</hi> under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing power of the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at ver. 5.) &amp; conſider whether
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154431:18"/> (I will not ſay any ſuch things have been brought in upon us, but) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may not juſtly for our ſins have ſuch brought in upon us; May we not juſtly fear to hear of ſuch a <hi>work wrought in our</hi> dayes, as to <hi>move all to regard and wonder marvellouſly,</hi> as ſcarcely to be <hi>believed though it be told us?</hi> May we not juſtly fear to hear of ſome <hi>bitter and haſty Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> marching <hi>through the breadth of the Land, to poſſeſſe the dwelling places that are not theirs?</hi> And may we not fear to hear of ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, Chap. 1. ver. 8. 9, 10, 11. <hi>Their horſes alſo are ſwifter than the Leopards, and are more fierce than the evening wolves: and their horſemen ſhall ſpread themſelves, and their horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall come from far, they ſhall fly as the Eagle that haſteth to eat. They ſhall come all for violence: their faces ſhall ſup up as the Eaſt winde, and they ſhall gather the captivity as the ſand. And they ſhall ſcoffe at the Kings, and the Princes ſhall be a ſcorn unto them:</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:154431:19"/> 
               <hi>they ſhall deride every ſtrong hold: for they ſhall heap duſt and take it. Then ſhall his mind change, and he ſhall paſse over, and offend, imputing this his power unto his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Look again into the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Prophet, beginning at verſe 12. of the firſt Chapter (where the Prophet expoſtulates with God, <hi>why the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous than himſelf, &amp;c.)</hi> and may we not juſtly fear to finde men made as the fiſhes of the Sea, and as the creeping things that have no Ruler over them? to finde men catching others with the Angle, and with the Drag, and then <hi>ſacrificing to their Nets,</hi> and <hi>burning incenſe to their Drag? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Look lastly</hi> upon the judgments denounced upon the enemies of Gods people, and conſider for what cauſes, and withall whether we have not cauſe to fear being among ſome that commit ſuch ſins; A woe is denounced againſt the <hi>Chaldean</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:154431:19"/> becauſe <hi>he enlarged his deſire as Hell, and could not be ſatisfied, but increaſed that which was not his, and how long?</hi> It is threatned that they ſhould <hi>riſe up ſuddenly that ſhould bite him? and awake that ſhould vex him, &amp;c? that the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the people ſhould ſpoile him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had ſpoiled many, &amp;c.</hi> Chap. 2. 6, 7, 8. A woe is denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him <hi>that coveteth an evill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe to his houſe, that he may ſet his neſt on high, and be delivered from the power of evill.</hi> Ibid. ver. 9. Woes alſo are denounced againſt <hi>bloody builders,</hi> and againſt <hi>ranting drunkards,</hi> as well as ſuperſtitious foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Idolaters afterward in that Chap, and may we not fear ſitting among ſuch perſons as are under ſuch woes? Have not we cauſe to fear the <hi>voice of the rod,</hi> (Micah 6. 9.) as well as <hi>of the Word?</hi> I ſuppoſe ye grant it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Therefore in the next place I exhort you to examine whether ye fear as ye ſhould, and to take on ſuch
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154431:20"/> a fear and trembling at the words, and working of the great God as is meet; Even ſuch a fear as may draw towards God, and drive on to prayer; ſuch a fear as may be the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſdom, in this reſpect, that it makes us fly unto the Name of our God, as unto a ſtrong Tower, either to keep us from, or to defend us in the midſt of Dangers, and bring us with ſafety, and comfort out of them. And ſo make fear, not an obſtacle, or impediment to duty, but a preparative unto duty. As <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>tis ſaid, <hi>Noah being warned of God, moved with fear, pepared an Ark, &amp;c.</hi> (Heb. 11. 7.) ſo let godly fear in us ſet us a preparing ſomewhat that may tend to the ſecuring of the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Gods people, at leaſt in way of Prayer, as doth the Prophet in our Text. To whoſe Prayer of Faith I now paſſe over.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[O Lord, revive thy work in the midst of the years, &amp;c.</hi> Here are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers terms to be opened before we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154431:20"/> can well pitch upon matter of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. As</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What is the [work] of God.</item>
               <item>2. What Gods [reviving] of his work.</item>
               <item>3. What [the midſt of the years] in which he is prayed to revive it.</item>
               <item>4. What is [making known] in the midſt of years.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I know there is another reading of part of theſe words by the Greek Septuagint; For that clauſe <hi>[in the midſt of years make known]</hi> they read to this ſenſe, <hi>[in the midſt of two living Creatures thou ſhalt be known]</hi> and much deſcant there is among Expoſitors, Ancient and Modern, upon that paſſage ſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; generally they underſtand Chriſt for the party to be known: but who the two living Creatures ſhould be in the midſt of whom he was to be known, they vary much in opinion; <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and <hi>Origen</hi> his, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Writers theirs; but becauſe that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154431:21"/> is a reading not approved by judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, either Proteſtant, or Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Expoſitors, I will not ſpend time in any particular recital of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent opinions.</p>
            <p>There is another reading of the firſt clauſe of this Prayer in the Old Engliſh Tranſlation, varying from our New (which it may be ſome of you finde in the Books you uſe) it runs thus, <hi>[Revive thy work in the midſt of the people]</hi> but why they ſhould render the ſame Hebrew word [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] ſo differently in the two clauſes, eſpecially ſince it ſignifies [years] and not [people] for ought I have found, I cannot finde any ſatisfactory reaſon. Taking therefore our laſt Tranſlation to be moſt conſonant to the Original, I keep to it, and ſo come to the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words. Wherein my chief regard ſhall be unto that litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſenſe which the conſideration of the Context leads us unto.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:154431:21"/>
            <p> Firſt then, what <hi>work of God may here be meant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I propound it to you in a double notion, but hardly ſeparable; take we it partly for the people of God themſelves: For his Covenanted people are his ſpecial work, or a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial piece of his workmanſhip, and he hath ever accounted his Church his peculiar above the generality of mankind, in and upon whom he hath given proofs and evidences of his moſt excellent vertues and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes. <hi>Ask of me (ſaith he) things concerning my ſonnes, and concerning the work of my hands command ye me,</hi> Iſa. 45. 11. See alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 21. and 61. 3. There ſonnes and the work of Gods hands are made Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyma. <hi>The Lord will perfect that which concerneth me; forſake not the work of thine own hands,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 138. 8. Accounting himſelf in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner the work of Gods hands; Conſonant to this the Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church of Believers under
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154431:22"/> the New Teſtament ſaith, <hi>We are his workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, &amp;c.</hi> Eph. 2. 10.</p>
            <p>But again, take we this work part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the work of Gods gracious Providence in behalf of his people, <hi>Status populi, vel Eccleſiae,</hi> as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſpeaketh; And ſignally here in our Text is the deliverance and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his people from under the power and captivity of the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Babylonians looked at; As is manifeſted by the Context.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>What may this reviving of the work of God be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be reduced unto two heads alſo;</p>
            <p>One is, <hi>The preſerving alive of the work of God,</hi> (for the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Piel, as it is here uſed, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>ſimpl. Vivum conſervare,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 29) <hi>All they that be fat upon earth ſhall eat and worſhip: all they that go down to the duſt ſhall bow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and none can keep alive his own ſoul.</hi> And thus it refers to Gods
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154431:22"/> work in the firſt ſenſe, not in reſpect of the life of individual perſons of the Church, ſo much as in reſpect of the generality or community of the Church, <hi>q. d.</hi> preſerve thy Church alive, conſerve a body of people to thy ſelf alive, let not that whole workmanſhip of thine periſh: nor the work of grace in thy people, (that may be alſo underſtood) for people do not live as Gods people, or as his Church, unleſſe the life of grace and holineſſe be preſerved alive in them.)</p>
            <p>But another thing is, <hi>The reſtoring of the ſtate of the people of God,</hi> (for ſo the Hebrew word alſo ſignifies, as in 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 11. 8. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4. 2.) and thus it refers unto the work of God in the ſecond acception, <hi>q. d.</hi> Reſtore thy people againe to their former ſtate of livelihood, or a liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wherein they were before; They ſhall be but as in ſtate of civil death while they lie in thraldom and ſervitude under the Chaldeans,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154431:23"/> and thou haſt intimated by the Viſion of grace which I have ſeen, that thy people ſhall not die, but ſhall live by faith, and that their enemies and oppoſers lie under thy woes and curſes, and ſo ſhall come to ruine and deſtruction; and therefore be pleaſed to put life and vigour into that work of thine, in behalf of thy people, or as ſome others gloſs it, <hi>Effice, ſuſcita, adimple,</hi> effectuate it, rear it up, accompliſh it. <hi>Opus enim dum non impletur, quaſi mortuum cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetur, &amp; oblivione ſepultum.</hi> Sanctius. And it is uſual with the Hebrews, as we all may perceive by the tenour of Scripture, to attribute life Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically unto things properly without life, and to call their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and reflouriſhing again, from a weak, decayed, broken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, a reviving, &amp;c. But now for the time,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What may <hi>[the midſt of years] be,</hi> that he thus iterates?</p>
            <p>Beloved, there is ſuch variety of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154431:23"/> Expoſitions given of this circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance among the Learned, that I ſhould ill husband my time to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate them, unleſs it would be to better purpoſe. This only I ſhall doe; firſt, touch briefly upon ſome that I cannot cloſe with, and why, and then lay before you that only which I take to be intended chiefly by the Prophet.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I take not this Phraſe barely to ſignifie <hi>[Intra annos praefinitos &amp; deſtinatos à Deo]</hi> within the compaſs of the years appointed by God (as ſome note <hi>medium</hi> to be taken <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſice, &amp; vulgariter,</hi> as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 2 9. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 2.) for I conceive, that though this be a truth, that God did, and will fulfill his determined work within his appointed time for them, or in <hi>plenitudine temporis,</hi> in the fulneſs of time determined yet this is a ſenſe that falls too ſhort of the Emphaſis of the doubling of this Phraſe in our Text, which may ſeem to import more than ſo.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:154431:24"/>
            <p> Yet ſecondly, neither do I take the midſt here <hi>(Geometricè &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisè)</hi> for the midſt according to a preciſe meaſure, as ſome do; For they that think he prayes that this reviving work of God might be wrought either about the middle of the years of the worlds duration, preſuming it ſhall laſt 6000. years, or juſt between <hi>Samuels</hi> Prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Chriſt his coming, or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (ſuppoſing juſt 490. years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that Prophet and the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and as many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Captivity and Chriſt) they build upon uncertainties, and that in the judgement of our lateſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Annotators, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What conſtruction then may we make of this expreſſion? The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be taken up, as I conceive <note place="margin">
                  <hi>As the Pſalmiſt prayed for himſelf, or rather in behalf of the Church,</hi> Pſ. 102. 23, 24.</note> with thoſe whom I account moſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, in theſe two particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In the midſt of the years,</hi> i. e. In the middle courſe of thy Church or people, while yet they are not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154431:24"/> grown up to a maturity or ripeneſs of age, ſuffer them not to periſh, but hold them up in life. Now that ancient people of God (ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> and our <hi>Genevian</hi> Annotators after him) came not to their fulneſſe of age till Chriſt, and therefore ſhould they not have been held up in a Church frame till then, they had ſunk as it were in the flower, or middle of their age, therefore he prayes thus, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In the midſt of years,</hi> i. e. <hi>illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum calamitoſorum &amp; infaelicium dierum, &amp;c.]</hi> of thoſe calamitous and unhappy dayes or years, when thy people ſhall be under the Chaldean bondage, when they ſhall be tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled headlong into miſeries, and be even overwhelmed with the waves of afflictions ruſhing in upon them, and over them, then do thou revive thy work, thy work of promiſed grace and goodneſs on their behalf. <hi>[Etiamſi videmur destinati eſſe morti, tamen nos reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> ſo <hi>Calvin]</hi> And
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154431:25"/> this I take to be the moſt genuine ſenſe of this expreſſion; This <hi>midſt of years,</hi> being as emphatical as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids midſt of troubles,</hi> Pſal. 138. 7. or <hi>the mountains being carried into the midſt of the Seas</hi> Pſal. 46. 2, &amp;c. But to proceed to the laſt Quere.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, what means that abrupt ſpeeh <hi>[make known] in the midſt of &amp;c.</hi> what would he have made known? Truly 'tis very eaſie to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both what, and how, by refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the foregoing words, <hi>viz.</hi> Make known thy reviving, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived work, &amp;c. Let it be actually ſeen that it is thy work, that ſuch people are thine, and that ſuch works of Providence for them are thine; let them, and all the world about take notice of it; And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in ſo doing, make know what a God thou art, as for wiſdom, and truth, and power, and other excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, ſo for mercy, <hi>in wrath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring mercy,</hi> as follows in the laſt clauſe; Of which excellent and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154431:25"/> comfortable ſentence I ſhall be able to ſpeak but briefly, and that as a ground onely of that one point I ſhall ſpeak unto for our inſtruction, which I gather up out of this branch of the Uſe, thus</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> There be good grounds for the people of God to build their faith and prayers upon, that God will preſerve his Church, and reſtore it unto a comfortable condition in the midſt of the greateſt dangers or miſeries they can fall into in this life. Or thus, Gods people may rely on him for reviving grace amidſt their moſt perplexed, deſperate, and (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to man) deadeſt condition. When there is otherwiſe no hope of recovery, they may hopefully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves unto him. I take the Obſervation in this frame, bcauſe I finde the Prophet praying to this purpoſe; and all warrantable pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are grounded upon Principles of Faith; and this Prayer was intended for the uſe of Gods people, and not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154431:26"/> for the Prophet himſelf onely, as if the Spirit of God from heaven had ſhewed them how God was to be ſought unto. And therefore we might ſtate the Point thus, That it is the duty of Gods people to pray unto him to revive his work in the midſt of moſt unlikely years. So <hi>Calvin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> Now that in the depth of diſtreſſes, the people of God have good ground of reliance on him for reviving grace, I will firſt ſhew by way of Inſtance, and then of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>By way of <hi>Inſtance,</hi> to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that God hath revived his work in the midſt of calamitous and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous times, beſides thoſe of the Babyloniſh Captivity; I will mind you but of two moſt memorable ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <note place="margin">Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> out of the Scriptures. We are not to omit that reviving was grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for which moſt directly this Prayer was made; In that God hath preſerved life of grace in his people
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154431:26"/> druing the Captivity, refreſhing and confirming them by his ſervants the Prophets, as <hi>Ezekiel, Daniel</hi> and others, leſt they ſhould deſpair, and utterly ſink with grief; and reſtored them, &amp;c. witneſſe <hi>Haggie,</hi> and <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie</hi> following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One before that Captivity, viz.</hi> Gods deliverance of his people out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> For in the midſt of the years of their bondage there under <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> while they were groaning heavily under it, and felt their preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, tasks, and burdens multiplyed upon them; then God ſent them reviving comfort by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and wrought their deliverance wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, when according to man they were out of all hope of any ſuch thing. And this is that caſe which this Prophet moſt of all commends to their Poſterity in this Prayer, as a ground of Faith by way of preſident; Though there be ſome mixed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in it to ſome other writings vouchſafed them in languiſhing and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154431:27"/> fainting caſes while they were in the Land of Canaan; Among other verſes, ſee the 13, 14, 15, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Another after the Babyloniſh Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, <hi>viz.</hi> The redemption of his people wrought by Chriſt. For in the midſt of years of ſad and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full condition, when his people were much degenerated and corrupted, though they had the ſecond Temple ſtanding amongſt them, yet much polluted in worſhip, as well as in other ſinfull courſes, and thereupon left deſtitute of Prophets for a time, and deprived of the Royal dignity among them, being ſubdued by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans: then was Chriſt ſent into the world, and when the hearts of the beſt were troubled with longing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pextation of a Meſſiah; <hi>Venit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus cum morbus creverit ad ſummum paroxyſmum;</hi> Then Chriſt came (as a great Phyſitian) when the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe was grown to the higheſt and ſharpeſt fit of it, then came he to work the Patients moſt neceſſary
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154431:27"/> ſpiritual deliverance; And this is that reviving act which divers, Pontificial Expoſitors at leaſt make the Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical ſenſe of our Text, and think it moſt intended by the Spirit in this place. But it may ſuffice to take knowledge of it as an inſtance for proof of a reviving work of God, and ſurely the moſt eminent of all other to ſpiritual conſideration; For certainly look how much their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance out of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſurpaſſed that out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſo much, and more, doth this ſpiritual deliverance by Chriſt ſurpaſſe that out of <hi>Babylon. Jer.</hi> 16. 14 15. and 23. 6, 7, 8. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore behold the dayes come, ſaith the Lord, that it ſhall no more be ſaid; The Lord liveth that brought up the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael <hi>out of the land of</hi> Egypt: <hi>But, The Lord liveth, that brought up the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>from the Land of the North, and from all the Lands whither he had driven them: and I will bring them again into their Land, that I gave unto their Fathers. In his</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:154431:28"/> 
               <hi>dayes</hi> Judah <hi>ſhull be ſaved, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall dwell ſafely; and this is his Name whereby he ſhall be called</hi> THE LORD OUR RIGHTEOUS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES. <hi>Therefore behold, the dayes come, ſaith the Lord, that they ſhall no more ſay, The Lord liveth, which brought up the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>out of the Land of</hi> Egypt: <hi>But, The Lord li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, which brought up, and which led the ſeed of the houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>out of the North Countrey, and from all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys whither I had driven them, and they ſhall dwell in their own Land.</hi> And this is intimated to be ſo ſtrange and wonderfull, that the former ſhould not be remembred in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43. 18, 19. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not the former things, neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the things of old. Behold, I will do a new thing: now it ſhall ſpring forth, ſhall ye not know it; I will even make a way in the wilderneſs, and rivers in the deſert.</hi> And this is the Grandmother and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of ſuch ſpecial deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154431:28"/> of the people of God in ſundry quarters ſince experienced as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and of which it might be ſaid as of the threatned puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his people before, Chap. 1. 5. <hi>Behold ye, and regard, and wonder marvellouſly; for God worketh ſuch a work in your dayes, which ye will not believe, though it be told you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Sect.</hi> But from Inſtances come we to Reaſons, and there are ſo many inſinuated in our Text, as we need not at preſent look further for more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God may be relied on for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving grace in a dead condition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the <hi>Lord Jehovah,</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, to give a being unto what he pleaſeth, as the being of beings; and therefore able, as to give a being unto his threatnings, to actuate them, as the juſt ground of fear (before) ſo to give a being unto his promiſes and ſpeeches of grace, as the ground of hope. We ſay ſometimes of men that they are good to help at a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154431:29"/> dead lift (yet finde them often fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our greateſt expectations) but that can be ſaid of none in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God. And therefore we may believe, becauſe this makes for the glory of his power. This was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> ground of believing he ſhould have a childe by <hi>Sarah: He being fully perſwaded that what God had promiſed he was able to perform,</hi> therefore <hi>he conſidered not his own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy now dead, when he was about an hundred years old, neither yet the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of</hi> Sarah's <hi>womb, nor ſtaggered at Gods promiſe, but was ſtrong in faith, giving glory to God,</hi> Rom. 4. 18, 19, 20, 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the work here ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be revived, is Gods own work (as we heard) Now it ſtands upon the glory of his wiſdome to preſerve, and ſuſtaine his own ſpecial work, and not to let it fall and die under his hand, and not to leave it in the midſt unfitted, unfurniſhed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was that Prayer of the Pſalmiſt,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154431:29"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138. 8. <hi>The Lord will perfect that which concerneth me: thy mercy, O Lord, endureth for ever: forſake not the works of thine own hands.</hi> And therefore is that application made to God by the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 8, 9. <hi>Oh the hope of Iſrael, the Saviour thereof in the time of trouble, wherefore ſhouldeſt thou be a ſtranger in the Land? Why as a man astonied? Yet thou, O Lord, art in the midſt of us, and we are called by thy Name,</hi> (thy work) <hi>leave us not.</hi> Apply that other alſo in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 12. <hi>Lord, thou wilt ordain peace for us, for thou haſt wrought all our works in us, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe it concerns the glory of Gods goodneſſe and mercy; And it is his moſt excellent nature, in the the midſt of wrath to remember mercy, (as we finde in the laſt clauſe of our Text.)</p>
            <p>By the way enquire we, Is there any wrath, or furious indignation in God properly? No; He is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſuch paſſions as man is; <hi>Fury</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:154431:30"/> 
               <hi>is not in him,</hi> Iſa. 27. 4. The juſt and ſevere execution of puniſhments is called his wrath, &amp;c. Then why is his wrath ſaid to be ſomewhat ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up againſt his people?</p>
            <p>We anſwer, Gods wrath relates rather to the ſins than to the perſons of his people; The oppoſition riſing in him is not properly againſt his own work or people, but againſt Sathans work in them, or their own evil works.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, the ſtirring of his wrath or anger argues rather their apprehenſion and ſenſe, (who feele ſmart and affliction) than his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſtirred up againſt them, who doth but as a Chirurgian, or a Father, handle roughly, and correct his own for their good.</p>
            <p>Now hence we may the better conceive how 'tis ſaid in way of Petition, <hi>Lord, in wrath remember mercy;</hi> And this we are to conceive as an eminent excellency in God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Creature, that in wrath
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154431:30"/> he can and will remember mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his own workmanſhip, his Church, his people. How, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? By a merciful change of his work of Providence, and ſo giving real arguments of a mercifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. Now this the poore impotent creature cannot do when it is in paſſion; Man is ſubject to forget himſelf, and forget mercy in his wrath and fury, nor can he ſtop and ceaſe ſuddenly in his hot execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and turn his courſe, becauſe he hath not his paſſions at ſuch a check or command; but God can never forget himſelf, and he can eaſily hold up his ſevereſt executions; See <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 11. to 14. <hi>And Moſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Lord his God, and ſaid, Lord, Why doth thy wrath wax hot againſt thy people, which thou haſt brought forth out of the Land of Egypt, with great power, and with a mighty hand? Wherefore ſhould the Egyptians ſpeak, and ſay, For miſchief did he bring them out, to ſlay them in the</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:154431:31"/> 
               <hi>mountains, and to conſume them from the face of the earth: Turn from thy fierce wrath, and repent of this evil againſt thy people. Remember</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Iſrael <hi>thy ſervants, to whom thou ſwareſt by thine own ſelf, and ſaid'ſt unto them, I will multiply your ſeed as the ſtars of Heaven: and all this Land that I have ſpoken of, will I give unto your ſeed, and they ſhall inherit it for ever.</hi> Numb. 16. 46, 47, 48. <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Aaron, <hi>Take a cenſer, and put fire therein from off the Altar, and put on incenſe, and go quickly unto the Congregation, and make an atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them: for there is wrath gone out from the Lord; the plague is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. And</hi> Aaron <hi>took as Moſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and ran into the midſt of the Congregation: and behold, the plague was begun among the people, and he put on incenſe, and made an atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the people. And he ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the dead and the living, and the</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:154431:31"/> 
               <hi>plague was ſtayed.</hi> Pſal. 30. 5. <hi>For his anger endureth but for a moment; in his favour is life: weeping may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning</hi> and 138. 7. <hi>Though I walk in the midſt of trouble, thou wilt revive me, thou ſhalt ſtretch forth thine hand againſt the wrath of mine enemies, and thy right hand ſhall ſave me.</hi> And therefore in the midſt of the years of the afflictive ſenſe of Gods anger, there may be expectation of a mercifull reviving; therefore in the midſt of the cords and bonds of ſervitude, there may be expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a merciful breaking of them; <hi>Et ubi funis tenaciſſimus fuerit, rumpitur;</hi> Where the cord is ſtiffeſt, and ſtrongeſt, there it is broken ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly (ſaith <hi>Luther)</hi> when God is pleaſed to ſhew mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. This Point ſerves firſt to ſtir us upto a comfortable exerciſe of Faith, that God would be pleaſed to revive his work in the midſt of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154431:32"/> theſe years, &amp;c. Why? what years are they? I cannot ſay they are years of Gods peoples ſervitude or cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity under the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> or <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> (bleſſed be God for thoſe free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and liberties which are yet left unto us) But we are in the midſt of years of diſſentions even among brethren; of diviſions and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of hearts and wayes; of wars, and bloody hoſtilities between the profeſſed Members of the Church of Chriſt, of various concuſſions and ſhakings of Foundations; of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of tongues, tenents, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of eruptions, and overflowings of errors and blaſphemies; of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts caſt upon Gods Miniſters and Ordinances; and diſſentions or ſhatterings in pieces of Church Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies in manifold places; In a word, we are in the midſt of theſe years wherein it ſeems to me God hath dealt, or is dealing with our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as he threatned to deale with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in 2 Kin. 21. 13. (when
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154431:32"/> withall he threatned to make that people a prey, and ſpoile to their enemies) <hi>I will wipe Jeruſalem</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>as a man wipeth a diſh, wiping it, and turning it upſide down;</hi> God hath been wiping us, and wiping us, and in an overly way of cleanſing and purging us, but is he not ſo doing it as he is turning us upſide down? Surely then beloved, we are in the midſt of thoſe years wherein we need to pray that <hi>God would revive his work and make it known, and in wrath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, we know not what pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods God hath determined to ſuch years as we are in; we ſee not our ſigns; we have not any foretelling Prophets, as the Pſalmiſt complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Wee ſee not our ſigns, there is no more any Prophet, neither is there among us any that knoweth how long.</hi> It is not therefore with us as with the Jews, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. 12. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe when ſeventy years are accompliſhed, that I will puniſh</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:154431:33"/> 
               <hi>the King of Babylon, and that Nation ſaith the Lord for their iniquity, and the Land of the Chaldeans, and will make it perpetuall deſolations.</hi> And 29. 10. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord, That after ſeventy years be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Babylon, I will viſit you, and perform my good word toward you, in cauſing you to return to this place.</hi> Nor have we like grounds of duty as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> had, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 2, 3. <hi>In the firſt year of his reign, I</hi> Daniel <hi>underſtood by Books the number of the years, wherof the word of the Lord came to</hi> Jeremiah <hi>the Prophet, that he would accompliſh ſeventy years in the deſolations of</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. <hi>And I ſet my face unto the Lord God to ſeek by prayer, and ſupplications, with faſting, and ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and aſhes.</hi> Yet this we may, and ought to do.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hold to the general grounds and principles of faith. 1. Believe that God hath revived his people in the midſt of far ſadder years than we have yet ſeen, according to foregoing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:154431:33"/> inſtances, and others that might be given. And 2. Believe (and therefore the rather) that God can revive his work in the moſt ſeeming difficult caſes. And 3. Believe that God will not forſake his own work to leave it to ruine, or under imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and a languiſhing condition continually; And 4. Believe that God is of ſuch infinite mercy, that in wrath he will remember it, &amp;c. But I commend that of <hi>Bernard</hi> to conſideration as an approved truth, <hi>Deus olcum miſericordiae ponit in vaſe fiduciae.</hi> But then</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt not faile to do, what we in this Congregation are ſolemnly in doing this day, <hi>viz.</hi> we muſt ply God by prayers; For we know that whatever God determines to his people, though they know he hath determined it, yet he requires and expects his people ſhould ſeek unto him concerning it. See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 37. therefore did <hi>Daniel</hi> ſo pray, &amp;c. Much more ought we, in caſes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:154431:34"/> wherein we have no circumſtantial grounds of aſſurance, &amp;c. that we may obtain at length aſſurance and eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This may ſerve more ſpecially to ſtir up to ſeek God for a reviving of his work of Reformation in the Church, in the midſt of theſe years of diſturbance and hinderance of it. For my part, I take that to have been the work of God which was ſet afoot ſome years ſince in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for a Reformation in our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worſhip, Government, and Diſcipline; But how hath it now, and that for a good while lien ſtill almoſt, and how hath it been caſt back! How have cloſe counter-workers undermined it! and open enemies oppoſed it! how miſerably is it defaced! How do ſome Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations out-face it! And how do ſcoffers mock at it, like thoſe <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi> Nehem. 4. 2. will theſe few <hi>Jews</hi> revive the ſtones out of the the heaps of the rubbiſh, &amp;c? And
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:154431:34"/> we could point at the cauſes of all this; Mainly, The not counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing and furthering of the work of Civil Authority; But beloved, if it be Gods work begun for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as many of us here, I preſume, doubt not but it is) we may believe it ſhall be revived, and perfected ſooner or later againſt all unlikeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods; And accordingly we may pray that in the midſt of the years of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likelihood it may be revived; that inſtead of having our Land darkned over us in the clear day, and our Sun ſet at noon, (a curſe denounced <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 9.) light may ariſe unto the Church in the midſt of obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c. <hi>(Iſa.</hi> 58. 10.) and ſo ſtrength be raiſed in the midſt of weakneſſe, and livelineſſe ſpring up in the midſt of dying languiſhings. We may uſe that argument in reſpect of this work, which the people of God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>And the work hath had but a little revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, as</hi> Ezra 9. 8.</note> uſed, or was uſed for them in reſpect of their Land, <hi>(Iſa.</hi> 63. 17, 18.) The <hi>people of thy holineſſe have enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:154431:35"/> 
               <hi>it but a while,</hi> and in a ſmall ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp;c. But to draw to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Would we have God revive this work for his people? Then we muſt pray alſo that God would revive his work in his people, and with it his people themſelves; and each of us is to look that it be revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in himſelf. What work is this?</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The life</hi> of Faith in the main. Remember, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by Faith</hi> (Chap. 2. 4.) that is, Faith ſhall be a principle of life exerciſing many lively acts in them: and they ſhall attain to the life of Reſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Comfort by believing Gods promiſes; And therefore we are not to lie down in any dejections<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondences of mind through diſtruſt of Gods power or promiſes in any caſe that may conduce moſt to his glory in his peoples good.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Spirit of prayer for the reparation of Zion, the ſpiritual
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:154431:35"/> reſtorement of the Church; for when the Lord ſhall ſtir up his ſervants more generally and heartily to pray with melting compaſſionate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons toward the ſpiritual dilapidations, &amp; deformities of his Churches, it will be a good ſign that the ſet time to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor his Zion is come. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13, 14. <hi>Thou ſhalt ariſe, and have mercy upon Zion: for the time to favour her, yea the ſet time is come. For thy ſervants take pleaſure in her ſtones, and favour the duſt thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3ly. Reſolutions for beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in behalf of the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; This concerns you all, beloved, in your ſeveral places; and therefore to be far from being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> through worldly and carnal ends, inſtead of being its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters and advancers; and they that have pretended to build with Gods people, when they have intended to hinder (as they in <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. 2, 3.) God will diſcover them. But more eſpecially this concerns you, my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154431:36"/> and much reſpected Brethren of the Provincial Aſſembly, to look that you put forth revived ſpirits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward this work. If that were true, <hi>(ſano ſenſu) Jupiter, quos ſervare vult, ſuſcitat;</hi> then 'tis as true,<hi>—eos, per quos ſervare vult, &amp;c.</hi> If God quicken up thoſe whom he will ſave, then thoſe by whom he will ſave o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers inſtrumentally. O let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore through grace, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] ſtir up the gifts and graces of God in us, let us quicken up our ſelves to uſe all counſels and endeavours for the furtherance of Gods Church-work; and joyntly attend upon, and proſecute all thoſe good means ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our truſt undertaken, whereby it may be carried on for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, waiting on God for the iſſues of all our prayers, and all our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, which ſhall ſeem beſt to his heavenly wiſdom. However events ſhall fall out to us in our time, reſolve as our Prophet doth infer, ver. 17, 18. <hi>Although the fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:154431:36"/> 
               <hi>ſhall not bloſſome, neither ſhall fruit be in the vines: the labour of the Olive ſhall faile; and the fields ſhall yeeld no meat, the flock ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there ſhall be no herd in the ſtalls: Yet I will rejoyce in the Lord: I will joy in the God of my ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:154431:37"/>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:154431:37"/>
            <head>Chriſts counſel to the Church of <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Rev. 3. 11.</bibl>
               <q>Hold that faſt which thou haſt, that no man take thy crown.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are a parcel of the words of Chriſt immediately direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the Angel of the Church in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphia;</hi> but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to that whole Church, and every Member of it; yea intended for the good of other Churches alſo,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:154431:38"/> and therefore of ours; For <hi>he that hath an ear, let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith unto the Churches;</hi> It is the common <hi>Epiphonema</hi> which our Lord ſubjoyns to all his Epiſtles un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches, written ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the dictate of his ſpirit, by the pen of his Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> in the ſecond and third Chapters of this Book. He would have every one that hath an hearing ear, to lend his attention to that which is ſpoken by his ſpirit to what Church ſoever, in that ſuch is the general nature of all Churches, and Church-Members, as either they do, or may ſtand in need of all ſuch divine admonitions as are addreſſed occaſionally to any of them.</p>
            <p>Now whether thoſe ſeven particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches written unto by our Lord in this Context, were Types of ſeveral Churches of ſeveral conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and temperaments and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to follow in after-times by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence, I will forbear to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154431:38"/> aſſert poſitively, though I cannot but ſay what I think, that the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one of our own Worthies was very bright and clear in finding out thoſe ſuitable correſpondencies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe ſeven, and others ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding down to this preſent age re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively.</p>
            <p>Now for that Church in <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia</hi> (to which my Text is part of that which was written) this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable concerning it, that it &amp; that of <hi>Smyrna</hi> were the only Churches of all the ſeven which our Lord Chriſt openly reproved not at all, wheras he found ſomething reproveable in all the reſt; as on the other ſide, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable concerning that of the <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans,</hi> that it was the only Church of the ſeven which Chriſt commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not at all, whereas he took notice of ſomething commendable in all the reſt; and why this? not becauſe there was nothing faulty or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in thoſe of <hi>Smyrna</hi> and <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> but to ſhew how much the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:154431:39"/> Lord favoureth humble modeſty: nor becauſe there was nothing good in that of <hi>Leodicea,</hi> but to ſhew how much the Lord diſliketh proud vain-glory. But I wave ſuch general Obſervations.</p>
            <p>I draw nigh to the words read unto <note place="margin">Sect.</note> you; And not to take up any of our time with an exact Analyſis of Chriſt his Epiſtle to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> becauſe. I ſhall go near to draw all the lines from the utmoſt circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance of it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the center of my Text, know only that after he had given teſtimony to the preſent good that was in her (ver. 8.) and aſſurance of after goodneſs he would ſhew to her (ver. 9, 10.) both in ſubduing diſguiſed Adverſaries, and in preſerving her under tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he comes in the words I have hinted upon, to exhort her unto duty upon a double motive.</p>
            <p>The duty is, To <hi>to hold faſt that which ſhe had. Brevis eſt hortatio, ſed Emphatica valde. Pareus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt motive (which is placed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154431:39"/> in the front) is taken from the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe of Chriſt his coming <hi>[behold, I come quickly.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond (which follows in the rear) is from the poſſibility of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon neglect of that duty <hi>(that no man take thy Crown.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of the duty. Touching which, take up this Obſervation, that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It concerns the best of Gods</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Obſer.</note> 
               <hi>Churches and people to hold faſt that which they have.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I purpoſe to handle this Point (which is the principal in the Uſe) ſo as ye ſhall perceive it reacheth not only Church-Officers, but alſo Church-members, and thoſe of what condition ſoever, this duty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of univerſal concernment to all Gods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>people, though I may interlace ſomething that will bear reſpect to Church-Angels, and Officers. For the opening of this, conſider we</p>
            <p n="1">1. What it is which the Churches and people of God reſpectively are to hold faſt, ſince every thing that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154431:40"/> every one hath is not worthy to be held faſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How they are to hold that faſt, or what their faſt holding is in way of duty.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That which <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> (and ſo other approved Churches of Chriſt) had worthy to be held faſt, was,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Word of God, and the Name of God; <hi>thou hast kept my Word,</hi> and haſt <hi>not denyed my Name,</hi> (ſaid Chriſt, ver. 8.) Under this Word, and Name of God, &amp;c. is to be underſtood that whole truth whereby God in Chriſt had reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and manifeſted himſelf and his will unto his Church; whereby his Church knows what he is, and what he hath done, and what he hath willed and commanded his people to believe and do. Hence it was ſaid to the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> (ver. 3.) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how thou haſt received, and heard, and hold faſt, &amp;c. Part of which truth <hi>Philadelphia</hi> is minded
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:154431:40"/> of ver. 7. in that deſcription of Chriſt, from his 1. <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> 2. <hi>Truth,</hi> and 3. <hi>Having the key of David:</hi> (which three Branches point at his three Offices, <hi>Prieſtly, Prophetical, Kingly,</hi> as ſome judiciouſly learned think.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Ordinances of God for Goſpel worſhip, and Church Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations are inſinuated in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text as enjoyed by <hi>Philadelphia:</hi> For (mark it) Chriſt remembers her that he had <hi>ſet before her an open door, and no man could ſhut it,</hi> (ver. 8.) <hi>i. e.</hi> He had given her fair opportunities, and open and large means for the propagating of the Goſpel, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of Goſpel-work, many bars of obſtruction and hindrance being removed out of the way; So that Goſpel-Adminiſtrations had free courſe or paſſage among them, as 'tis ſaid it had among the Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, (2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 1.) Yea, we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from part of his Title which he purpoſely takes up in writing to her,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:154431:41"/> 
               <hi>(viz. He that hath the key of David)</hi> that he had not onely uſed his key for opening to her, but likewiſe given her the keys both of Doctrine and Diſcipline Miniſterial under himſelf to open and ſhut unto others. And no doubt this Church was not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that (according to her pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) which was commended in that of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> (cap. 2. 2.) <hi>viz. in not bearing with thoſe that were evil,</hi> but <hi>trying them which ſaid they were A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and finding them lyars, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Good works or practice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God. For 'tis the firſt part of Chriſt his teſtimony given to her, that <hi>He knew,</hi> (i. e. approved) <hi>her works</hi> (at the beginning of v. 8.) And what might her works be? Doubtleſs of as good account as any of her ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; works of charity, and ſervice, and faith, &amp; patience, as were her ſiſters of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> (cap. 2. 19.) And for pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience it is expreſſed here (ver. 10.) <hi>that ſhe keep the word of his patience,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:154431:41"/> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> ſhe exerciſed patience accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt his word and preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So that (to ſumme up all, and according to the tenour of other Scriptures compared with this,) if the people of God be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the general notion, All that which they are to hold faſt, is, 1. ſoundneſſe of Doctrine, and 2. Holineſſe of life and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which are mentioned together in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 19. <hi>Holding faith and a good conſcience, &amp;c.</hi> To hold faith there, is to hold the Doctrine of faith, or to <hi>hold faſt the form of ſound words;</hi> as 'tis phraſed, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. And ro hold a good conſcience, is to hold ſuch a practice according to that rule of faith, as an enlightned conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may witneſſe to be good, or to be rightly conſciencious in walking and working according to that rule.</p>
            <p>Again, if the people of God be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered collectively, as embodied together in a Church frame and order,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:154431:42"/> that which they are to hold faſt, is, thoſe Church-Ordinances which Chriſt hath given them, whether about duties of worſhip to God, or government among themſelves, or about the enjoyment of thoſe liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or priviledges or powers which he hath granted them. In reference to which under-Ordinances, the moſt judicious underſtand the Apoſtle ſpeaking thus to <hi>Timothy,</hi> I <hi>charge thee in the ſight of God (&amp;c.)</hi> that <hi>thou keep this Commandment,</hi> (i. e. that body or rule of Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment laid down in the premiſes) <hi>without ſpot, unrebukeable, untill the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Tim, 6. 13. 14. This for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that is to be held faſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> Next for the manner of holding faſt, what is it? The Holy Ghoſt uſeth ſundry words in ſeveral places, which are all of them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times rendred by our Tranſlators in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe terms of holding faſt, yet of ſomewhat different importment.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:154431:42"/> But by collection of them together we may more fully take up the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this duty. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 13. <hi>Hold fast the form of ſound words,</hi> he ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>i. e.</hi> hold them as having and retaining them by thee in poſſeſſion; But there is more than that barely in this duty. For when Chriſt bids the Church of <hi>Sardis (ſupra</hi> ver. 3.) <hi>Remember what thou haſt received, and heard, and hold faſt, (&amp;c.)</hi> his word is [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>i. e.</hi> hold, or keep, or obſerve with all diligence, as that which is committed to ones carefull cuſtody; But yet there is more imported in this duty; For when Chriſt bids the Church in <hi>Thyatira, That which ye have already, hold faſt till I come,</hi> (cap. 2. 25.) his word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the ſame word radically is uſed here in our Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> hold faſt ſtrongly; uſe not onely a carefull eye in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but put to they utmoſt ſtrength
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:154431:43"/> in holding faſt that which thou haſt, that keeping it vigorouſly, thou mayſt keep it alſo perſeverantly and conſtantly to the end. And a perſeverant holding faſt is here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by Chriſt (as well as cap. 2. 25.) as may be gathered from the annexed Motives. Now unto this ſtrong and vigorous holding faſt of Truth and Holineſſe, Faith and good Conſcience, there is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firm purpoſe of heart, and ſtedfaſt reſolution of will to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the profeſſion of ſound faith and Doctrine, and in the execution of Gods commands, according to place and power, and in the practice of holineſſe, &amp;c. If there be not firſt ſtrength in the will and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there will be none found in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal practice and exerciſe. The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the heart conduceth much to the vigour of the hand or foot; Hence it was that <hi>good man, and full of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> exhorted the Chriſtians
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:154431:43"/> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> that <hi>with purpoſe of heart</hi> 
               <note place="margin">If there be weakneſſe in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, there will be weakneſs in the joynts; if weakneſs in the heart, weakneſſe in hands and limbs.</note> 
               <hi>they would cleave unto the Lord,</hi> Act. 11. 23. And <hi>the Apoſtle Paul</hi> calls upon us <hi>to hold faſt the profeſsion of our hope without wavering,</hi> (without declining or tottering any way) therefore in a fixed and firmly ſetled manner, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Vigorous putting forth of ſtrength in the way of conteſtation with others, for the maintenance and defence of Truth, and Purity of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Worſhip, and holy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and practice, ſo farre as is warrantable in a regular way; We are to <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith which was once delivered to the Saints,</hi> Jude 3. and to <hi>ſtand faſt in the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, that we be not entangled again with the yoke of bondage,</hi> Gal. 5. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what need is there of ſuch ſtrong actings to hold faſt Truth and Holineſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is need of ſome ſtrength in a double reſpect.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:154431:44"/> 1. To hold up againſt inward faintings and languiſhings; We know that every thing is ready to fall and drop out of our hands when our natural ſpirits faile within us; and we are faine to take Cordials ſometimes to ſtrengthen our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks to retain what is taken down, which otherwiſe either through nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeouſneſs or other weakneſſe would be quickly caſt up again. So it is too often in the caſe of the failing of gracious ſpirits in Chriſtians through ſpiritual faintings, they are too ready to let fall divers truths of God, and to ſtick in the profeſſion of them, and to let fall practical ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of holineſs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> let diſſolve away the regular aſſemblings of themſelves together. And all this ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through a nauſeating wearineſſe of ſuch things by the great gathering of ill humours, or through ſome cauſeleſſe fearfull puſillanimous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions; And therefore ſaid Chriſt to the Church at <hi>Sardis,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:154431:44"/> (ver. 2.) <hi>ſtrengthen the things that remain, which are ready to dye.</hi> The remaining good things in a Church of Chriſt, are ſometimes through the weakneſſe of inward Principles rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to languiſh and dye away, and therefore need be ſtrengthened.</p>
            <p>Again, there is need of ſtrength 2ly, To retain againſt external vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, or forcible attempts of others to wring from Chriſt what they hold of good, or to make them fling it away, or ſhake it off from them. <hi>Robore hic opus eſſe judicat, quia plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rima ſunt quae fidelibus haec dona ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutere poſſunt, niſi tenere omnibus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis contendant,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pareus in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum)</hi> We might be encouraged by many examples of Martyrs, yea ſome Heathen may be alluded to, as that of <hi>Attilius</hi> the Roman, who fighting for a Ship at Sea, held faſt on her with one hand after another till both were cut off: <hi>Valer. Max.</hi> another whoſe hands were off, held faſt with his teeth; ſo chriſtians ſhould <hi>mordicus</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:154431:45"/> 
               <hi>tenere.</hi> But I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more of this point by and by, under one of the Motives in the Context.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But it may be asked again, What need the people of God be charged with care of duty of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſince there be ſuch precious promiſes made unto them that the Lord will keep them, and preſerve them, and his graces in them, ſo that they ſhall never depart, or fall away from him, nor ever be plucked out of his hand; but be kept, by the power of God through faith unto ſalvation? See <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. 40. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 28, 29. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5. They that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Lord, ſhall retaine that which ſhall bring them, or ſuffice to accompany them to everlaſting glory and happineſs; and why then need they be ſolicitous about hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſt that which they have?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have to anſwer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For particular perſons, even
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:154431:45"/> ſuch as are elect, and called, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded too of their intereſt in ſuch precious promiſes, they notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe promiſes, are obliged by command from God to look to their own ſelf-ſpiritual preſervation, and that in a ſubſerviency to Gods providence for the accompliſhment of his promiſes. It was not ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groundedly by that Ancient, (ſo it be rightly underſtood) <hi>Qui creavit te ſine te, non ſervabit te ſine te,</hi> &amp;c. God hath ordered moſt wiſely and juſtly, that the firſt ſpark of grace which he giveth to his beloved ones, ſhould be employed and improved inſtrumentally under his own ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme agency for both their preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and advance of their happy condition; Therefore (mark it) the fear which he puts into their hearts, that is, that holy circumſpect fear, (not ſecure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption) is made a preſervative for their not departing away from him, in that <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. 40. And though he
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154431:46"/> keep them by his own power, yet it it is through the continued acting and exerciſing of their faith that he keeps them unto ſalvation; In that 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es gathered in viſible communion and frame of Government, there be no promiſes made unto any of them, (for ought I have heard, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) nor ever were, that they ſhould be perpetually preſerved either without decay, or without diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore there is no cauſe why Church-members ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe and negligent in holding faſt thoſe Church-Ordinances, Liberties, and Priviledges which they enjoy at preſent, if they regard the good of that collective body whereof they are, becauſe they have no ground of promiſe to pretend for ſecurity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a ſuddain change and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Yea thirdly, ſuppoſe a promiſe made to a particular Church for its
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:154431:46"/> preſervation for a time, yet the Lord will not have that Church ſlacken her care, and endeavour of preſerving her ſelf, no not during that ſeaſon. My proof by way of inſtance is near at hand: Chriſt made a promiſe to this Church at <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia</hi> (in the verſe before my Text) that he would <hi>keep her from the hour of temptation that ſhould come upon all the world, to try them that do dwell upon the earth,</hi> and yet preſently he forewarns her to hold that faſt which ſhe had; This is very obſervable; She might not expoſtulate, Lord, ſince thou wilt keep me, what need I take any care of keeping my ſelf? No; Churches as Churches muſt learn to ſerve under Gods promiſes and providences for their own good as well as particular Chriſtians: And Gods known purpoſed indulgences ſhould not occaſion his ſervants neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences. How much more cauſe then have thoſe Churches to take this warning, which have no ſuch
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:154431:47"/> ſpecial promiſes made unto them, as none of the particular Churches of Chriſt (for ought I know) have at this day?</p>
            <p>Theſe things being in ſome ſort cleared, I ſhall peſent you with what I have further to ſay in the way of uſual improvement of the Doctrine delivered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. Firſt, I beſeech you to make uſe of this Point by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y of Caution in reference to the Object. We have heard what it is which the ſervants and Churches of Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively are to hold faſt. Now becauſe there is a tenacity, a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to hold faſt ſomething or other in every one, and yet every thing which one hath is not worth holding faſt, therefore let us try what it is only that we have; be ſure to hold faſt that which is good: ye know well the Apoſtles Precept, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 21. <hi>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good:</hi> we have found the things in kind, that ſingle Chriſtians, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:154431:47"/> Chriſtians in Church-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are to hold faſt reſpectively: <hi>viz.</hi> matter of Doctrine, and of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Moral practice, and of Church-adminiſtration; Now all theſe are to be proved, and then ſo farre as found good ſtedfaſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Here divers things might be ſpoken touching the buſineſſe of proving and trying.</p>
            <p>Touching the courſe taken for <hi>proving;</hi> what, would the Apoſtle have Chriſtians wander up and down into every Conventicle, or every corner to hear the broachers of all ſorts of Opinions? or, would he have Chriſtians adventure to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell into all Countries, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termingle in all ſorts of companies, to get information what all men hold, and all men practice? O no; Beloved, wofull experience in our times, ſhews that a number of light-headed, curious gadders, and travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, having no ballaſt of weighty judgement in them, are ſo toſſed up
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:154431:48"/> and down with the various kindes of Opinions and waves of mens pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, claſhing and breaking one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, that they ſcarce ever come to ſide at Anchor at Sea, much leſſe put in at any ſafe Harbor, but ſtill fluctuate as Scepticks in Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Antinomiſts in practice, and half Atheiſts at leaſt in both; We need not wander up and down for variety to bring under trial; for we may finde too much brought home to us to our own places, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe our judgements if we have any, and if not, to diſtract and diſquiet us.</p>
            <p>A great part of <hi>Solomons</hi> curious ſcarch experimentally was ſo unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and unſeemly, as we may ſuppoſe it coſt him a great deale of repentance afterward. I ſay no more of this.</p>
            <p>But then again, for what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily brought under our eye for proving, remember that our onely true teſt, or <hi>touchſtone,</hi> or rule for <hi>proving, is the written Word of God.</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:154431:48"/> And yet here we need begg of God ſound wiſdom how to make a right uſe of this proving touchſtone; for ſurely it is moſt groſly abuſed, and wreſted, and perverted among our people at this day, what through want of Learning, what through want of humility, becauſe they would be dogmatizing. And I fear there be crept in among them a number of Popiſh and profane witts, who though ſecret ſcoffers at the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are leaders into manifold Errors by counterfeiting very great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a reverence to Scripture Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and urging the letter of it, and expreſs commands, and examples from it, while in the mean time they aime at both the diſparagement of Scriptures, and the confuſion of their ſilly ſelf-conceited follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. The Lord direct us all to a right eſteem and uſe of holy Writ; for 'tis poſſible there may be ſuch found like thoſe of old who <hi>melted,</hi> and moulded their <hi>golden earings</hi> (of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:154431:49"/> Doctrines, if right uſed) into <hi>Idolatrous Images;</hi> And ſuch as can turn <hi>a braſen Serpent</hi> from a divine inſtitution, to become a ſuperſtitious Idol.</p>
            <p>Thus having conſidered well what courſe we take in the way of Trial, let us, (as was ſaid) <hi>hold faſt only that which is good;</hi> Onely pure and holy Doctrine, onely approvable, gracious practice ſuitable to ſuch Doctrine; and in Church-reſpects, whether as Paſtors and Teachers or other Eccleſiaſtick Officers, onely ſuch adminiſtrations, and wayes of Government as may be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the minde and word of our Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>It is obſervable, that duty of this nature in our Text, <hi>viz. to hold what was had already,</hi> is either expreſly, or implicitely charged upon every one of thoſe <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches written to by Chriſt, except that of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea;</hi> for all the reſt had ſomewhat commended in them, but ſhe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:154431:49"/> as if ſhe had nothing worthy to hold faſt; But why this? Had ſhe not much precious Doctrine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by her? Grant it, yet it ſeems while ſhe held her luke-warm temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in point of Government and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, all her Doctrine was as if it were not; O Beloved, that we had not yet amongſt us a number of old <hi>Laodiceans</hi> obſtructing what they can, all proceeding in way of a right<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wiſe, and ſober Reformation, and zealous onely to damp the zeale of people that way, and ſtifly to hold faſt humane ſuperſtitious inventions, and their proud vain-glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of them. The Lord ſoften and bend their ſpirits.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. A ſecond Uſe of this Point let be by way of <hi>Exhortation,</hi> or Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O that we would all ſtirre up our ſelves to all care and diligence to hold faſt what good we have, and let us all be ſtirred up thereunto at preſent.</p>
            <p>Surely there are very ſtrong Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154431:50"/> hereunto, which may eaſily be perceived, if we look about us. I ſhall only preſs a little thoſe two, which lie on either hand the duty in our Text, or what is equivalent thereunto.</p>
            <p>The firſt is in the beginning of the verſe, <hi>[Behold, I come quickly]</hi> ſaith the Lord Jeſus; A Motive taken from his quick apprehenſion unto them. Now that ſpeedy coming of his needs not to be underſtood meerly of a perſonal viſible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but of his coming in ſuch ways of providence, as wherein he was to be underſtood as vertually and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually preſent for the mannaging of them, and ſo we muſt needs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the phraſe, Chap. 2. 5, 16. <hi>Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and repent, and do the firſt works, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and will remove thy candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick out of his place, except thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Repent, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and will fight againſt them with the ſword of my mouth.</hi> Where his quick coming was doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:154431:50"/> in a way of puniſhment, or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement, &amp;c. But how are we here to underſtand Chriſt his quick coming?</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>In a way of Trial.</hi> He had intimated immediately before, that there was an <hi>hour of tentation coming upon all the world, to try them that dwelt upon the earth:</hi> and he is to be thought to be in that trial, profeſſing himſelf to be the <hi>(ſearcher of the reins and heart,</hi> Chap. 2. 23.) and here as referring unto it, he ſaith, <hi>Behold,</hi> [take notice] <hi>I come quickly, viz.</hi> to try you among other in that hour of temptation; what hour was that? Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately it ſignified (as ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors think with good conſent) that perſecution which ſoon after followed upon the Churches under the reign of <hi>Trajanus</hi> the Emperour, and in which perſecution <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia</hi> was tried as well as other. <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo</hi> the Geographer writes that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphia</hi> was <hi>[terrae motibus crebrò concuſſa]</hi> often ſhaken with Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes; Well, whatever natural, or
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:154431:51"/> proper Earthquakes, ſhe as a City with the region thereabout was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto, certainly as ſhe was a Church, both ſhe and others in thoſe Primitive times, were often ſhaken with Political Earthquakes, ſhaking violences and aſſaults by Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, threatning their ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And leſt this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhould not ſeem to reach us at this day, take notice, that in the judgement of many godly learned, there is now an <hi>hour of temptation</hi> drawing on upon the preſent reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches of Chriſt which ſweetly anſwer to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> (to ſay no more) wherein they are likely to be extreamly ſhaken, and ſo tryed to the purpoſe; Nay, be there not ſome ſymptomes that ſuch an hour is already entred upon ſome of them? Is there not an horrible tempeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready riſen among the <hi>poor reformed Churches in Piedmont,</hi> which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhaken divers of them in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſcattered them among the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:154431:51"/> Mountains, and ſome other neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring places where they may hope for no ſhelter? Now how ſoon, and how farre the like Earthquakes may ſhake other Churches and places, the Lord onely knows; but the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of a time of ſhaking triall to paſſe over all, may be ſufficient ground of warning to hold faſt what good we have; Never are men more in danger to let go what they have, than when they are terribly ſhaken: never were the <hi>Diſciples</hi> in more danger of taking ſcandal at Chriſt, and letting go their hold of him, than when <hi>Satan deſired to ſift,</hi> and <hi>winnow them as wheat,</hi> (Luke 22. 31.) Therefore in apprehenſion of ſuch a time, that the reformed Churches abroad, and we together with them may hold faſt that we have, They that ſeem to be <hi>as pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in the houſe of God,</hi> (Gal. 2. 9.) (though they be not uſed as that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical <hi>Simeon</hi> did thoſe Material Pillars before an Earthquake, yet)
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:154431:52"/> need ſuch a warning as he gave them, Stand faſt, for we ſhall be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>2ly, underſtand here Chriſt his coming quickly in <hi>a way of mercy</hi> to moderate the trial, &amp; to deliver from the power of temptation, <hi>q. d.</hi> I come quickly to reſtore thee; Thy troubles and trials ſhall not laſt long; The tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> were meaſured by dayes, and were called <hi>tribulations of ten dayes;</hi> (ſuppoſe years to be underſtood by dayes, as uſually in this book, that was no long time) But here the Churches time of temptation is meaſured, (I cannot ſay by hours, but) onely by an <hi>hour;</hi> it is foretold onely to be an hour, that is, a very ſhort time of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, And truely Beloved, ſuch ſhort trials 'tis conceived and hoped will be the remaining trials of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, how ſharp ſoever they may be for the while; But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their duration may be, ye know what the Apoſtle ſaid, that <hi>our</hi> (the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:154431:52"/> Churches) <hi>afflictions are but for a moment,</hi> (2 Cor. 4. 17.) Now therefore as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, what? <hi>Could ye not watch with me one hour?</hi> So I ſay, ſhall we not hold faſt what we have one houre, not one moment, after which all hard trials ſhall be over? O let this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us! Eſpecially, ſince we are to underſtand Chriſt his coming quickly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>In a way of judicature,</hi> to call men to an account, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute rewards according to their works; To ſhew himſelf gracious and bountifull to ſuch as do hold faſt the good they have till he come, and ſevere toward others. See Chap. 22. 12. <hi>And behold, I come quickly, and my reward is with me, to give to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man according as his work ſhall be.</hi> Heb. 10. 37. <hi>For yet a little while, and he that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry.</hi> James 5. 8. <hi>Be ye alſo patient; ſtabliſh your hearts: for the</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:154431:53"/> 
               <hi>coming of the Lord draweth nigh.</hi> But the meditation of this will carry me into the ſecond Motive following the duty in the latter part of this verſe; paſſe we therefore over unto it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[That no man take thy Crown,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Motive.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>i. e.</hi> that no man take away thy Crown, or that thy Crown be not taken away from thee? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hic idem eſt quod</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Matth. 5. 40. <hi>(Brightman)</hi> And doubtleſſe want of good hold faſt hath loſt many a Crown. It is an argument taken from the danger of loſing her Crown if ſhe did not hold faſt: But withall inſinuating a Crown aſſured unto her keeping faſt her hold. Well,</p>
            <p>Our firſt enquiry here may be, <hi>what means he by her Crown?</hi> It is taken two wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for that Crown ſhe had in ſome ſort already, <hi>viz.</hi> That honour which this Church had partly gotten, and was further to get by that holy
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:154431:53"/> Spiritual grave manner of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and obſervation of Gods Ordinances which carried that luſtre of excellency and Authority in it, as convinced the mindes, and affected the ſpirits even of Adverſaries, ſo that they which were formerly of the <hi>Synagogue of Satan, which ſaid they were Jews, (i. e.</hi> true worſhippers of God, and of the onely Church of God) <hi>but were not, ſhould come and worſhip before the face of that Church,</hi> and acknowledge her beloved of God, and honourable, ver. 9. And in ſome ſuch reſpect as this, did the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> call the <hi>Philippians</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> his <hi>Joy,</hi> and his <hi>Crown,</hi> Phil. 4. 1. 1 Theſ. 2. 19. For how came he to eſteem them ſo? In that God was pleaſed by his Miniſtery to tranſlate them out of darkneſſe into the kingdom of Chriſt Jeſus, and to make his Miniſtery inſtrumentally powerfull to bring them under the yoke of Chriſt and to lay down their former pride, and profeſſedly to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:154431:54"/> ſubject themſelves to the Goſpel of Chriſt, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 13.) yea, when perſons convinced ſhall be ready to fall down upon their face, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, and confeſſe that God is in his ſervants (and Ordinances) of a truth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 25.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For that ſuperexcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Crown, or higheſt honour and dignity in Heaven which God hath promiſed out of his free grace, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon thoſe who perſevere in Faith and obedience to the end; that which is called the <hi>Crown of life,</hi> Chap. 2. 10. the <hi>Crown of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 8. a <hi>Crown of glory that fadeth not away,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 4. Now Beloved, for the Argument;</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the former Crown it ſtands thus. If thou doſt not hold faſt what thou haſt, thou art like to loſe the glory of Goſpel-Miniſtery, and the due reverence and authority which it hath had hitherto more or leſſe in the hearts of men, and may yet further have if thou be not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:154431:54"/> unto thy ſelf, and negligent to retaine and keepe thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Priviledges which make for thy ſpiritual honour; And it is poſſible for a particular Church in time to loſe its Eccleſiaſtick Crown here below, as it fared long ſince with that Church of <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, In reſpect of the other Crown of life and glory never fading, the Argument ſtandeth thus. Thou hadſt need uſe all thy prudence, and diligence, and fortitude to hold faſt what thou haſt, and to perſevere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end, leſt being at a loſs of grace, thou be alſo at a loſs of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Thou standeſt by Faith, be not high-minded but fear,</hi> ſaid the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom</hi> 11. 20. And look we to our ſelves <hi>that we loſe not thoſe things which we have wrought, but that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a full reward,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> (2 Joh. 8.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> But doth not the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed danger and caveat upon it
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:154431:55"/> in this ſenſe infringe the certainty of the perſeverance, and ſalvation of the Saints?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, it doth not. For in the community of a viſible Church there is a mixture of Hypocrites with ſincere Profeſſors; Now Hypocrites may loſe the Crown of glory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they never had really either true Faith, or holineſſe, but onely ſeemed to have them, and therefore though they loſe that Crown which was propoſed to them to runne, and ſtrive and labour for, yet is not the tenure of divine Election in the leaſt weakened by their failing, becauſe though they were called externally, yet not elected, and never had the faith or grace of the Elect. And for ſincere Chriſtians, who onely are ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, though they ſhall not loſe the Crown prepared and reſerved for them, yet they have need of ſuch caveats as this.</p>
            <p>Partly to minde them, though they be kept by the power of God
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:154431:55"/> to ſalvation yet in themſelves there is a Principle of defection and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, and were they left unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they ſhould let go all grace, and loſe all glory, and therefore need be the more wary.</p>
            <p>Partly to keep them from looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and defection; for Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Admonitions from the mouth of God, and ſet on by the Spirit of God, are inſtrumental in Gods hand to ſtirre them up to du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and hold them in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſeverance. The premiſſes conſidered, O Beloved, how ſhould we be ſtrengthened in our reſolutions, and actuated in our ſtrongeſt endeavours to ſtand faſt, and hold faſt that truth, that grace, and all thoſe ſpiritual li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and priviledges beſtowed upon us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 3. A third Uſe of this point may be to give and take ſome <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections</hi> for the more effectual pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this Rule, ſince it is a thing both of ſo much difficulty, and of ſo
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:154431:56"/> great conſequence to obſerve it. In the way of hopefull means therefore be pleaſed to take notice of theſe few particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Would we hold faſt what good we have perſonally, and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally? Then take an humble recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of our own weakneſſe reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively. It is ſaid of this Church of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> a little before, at ver. 8. that <hi>ſhe had</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>a little ſtrength;</hi> (and, indeed this duty of holdfaſt is directed neither to live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perſons, nor meer impotent perſons in ſpiritual reſpects) but it was but a little ſtrength. So it was with her that was one of the beſt of the ſiſters; we are then to be humbly apprehenſive of the ſmalneſſe of our own ſtrength, even when we are at the beſt; And then beſides, we may reflect back, and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſome particulars we have not ſlipped back with <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>fallen from our firſt love,</hi> and whether we are not in ſome particulars in a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:154431:56"/> condition as <hi>Sardis,</hi> and ſo need to <hi>ſtrengthen the things which remain that are ready to dye;</hi> But I ſay we are to be humbly ſenſible of our little ſtrength at the beſt, and that will diſpoſe us to more care to hold faſt what we have, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take we, and keep we faſt hold on God by Faith, and in the frequent exerciſe of Prayer, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating <hi>Jacob in not letting of him go.</hi> He looks that his people ſhould do ſo; even to take <hi>hold of him and his ſtrength,</hi> (in a good ſenſe) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 5. not in a way of preſumptuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with him, but for our own ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port by him <hi>Stirre up our ſelves to lay hold on him,</hi> Iſa 64 7. For why? <hi>Qui habet habentem omnia, habet om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:</hi> ſo <hi>Qui retinet, &amp;c. In his own might ſhall no man</hi> (no Church) <hi>be ſtrong:</hi> but we may be able <hi>to do all things through Chriſt ſtrengthening us,</hi> and therefore we are alwaies to <hi>walk</hi> and act <hi>in the ſtrength of the Lord,</hi> (Pſal. 71. 16.) Maintain ſound
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:154431:57"/> Doctrine in the ſtrength of the Lord; keep the way of holineſſe in the ſtrength of the Lord; perform all Church-duties in the ſtrength of the Lord, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let it be our holy covetous aime to be getting more of that good which we are to hold faſt. Men of the world are ready to think that in externall things, if they be not on the increaſing hand, they are on the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing; And what ſhall we think of our condition in Spirituals? If we look into the Evangelical Parable of the <hi>ſervants</hi> that had <hi>Talents,</hi> or <hi>Pounds</hi> committed to their uſance, we may finde the <hi>evill ſervant</hi> there keeping his Talent, and <hi>wrapping it up in a napkin</hi> (and did he not then hold it faſt?) but that proved neither pleaſing to his Maſter, nor comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to himſelf, becauſe he ſhould have been imploying and improving it, which becauſe he was not, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was ſaid <hi>not to have,</hi> and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced <hi>to have that taken from him</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:154431:57"/> 
               <hi>which he onely ſeemed to have.</hi> For without ſome improvement a ſtock cannot long be kept entire together. Wherefore in ſpiritual things, belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if we would with <hi>Philadelphia hold faſt what we have,</hi> we muſt affect the commendation of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> (Chap. 2. 19) <hi>to have our laſt works more than our firſt,</hi> to advance in ſolid know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in true and ſincere holineſſe, and if it be poſſible, to have our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Church-Miniſtery, Church-Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, Church-Adminiſtrations better than our former. This I ſay muſt ſtill be our aime, or otherwiſe we ſhall be ſoon caſt backward; when men are in a broad wheele, either to crane up things from the earth, or to draw up baskets out of the water, they are ſtill ſteping for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or elſe they could not ſtay in the ſame place and circumſtances of poſture where they are, (as it is alſo with Birds in a turning bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage:) And ſo when Chriſtians or Church-Members are ſet into ſuch a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:154431:58"/> frame, as the wheele of occurrents is ſtill turning upon them, either they muſt be ſtill ſtepping forward, or elſe they cannot keep the ſame ſight of their ſtation, but be driven back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and overturned.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We muſt be induſtrious, and zealous in all the affairs which make for the preſervation and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what we have: I commend that cluſter of Apoſtolical precepts unto you in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 11. <hi>Be not ſloathfull in buſineſſe, (but) fervent in Spirit, ſerving the Lord.</hi> And theſe are connexed, and ſubordinate one to the other; Firſt, <hi>Not ſloathfull, i. e.</hi> neither altogether idle, nor remiſſe, or careleſſe how we do what we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be doing, how ſlowly, how ſeldom, how ſlightly; For he <hi>that is ſloathfull in his work, is brother to him that is a great waſter,</hi> (Prov. 18. 9.) ſo farre will he prove from a holder faſt of what he hath; For the ſloathful gets nothing, as the waſter ſpends all; and ſo in their emptineſs
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:154431:58"/> and needineſſe they come to ſhake hands together.</p>
            <p>Again, If we would not be ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, we muſt be <hi>fervent in Spirit;</hi> for ſloathfulneſſe is from coldneſſe of temper corporally, or ſpiritually: and activity is from heat and ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; ſo that unleſs one be ſomewhat zealous, he cannot be conſtantly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious. As the light is gone in a manner, when the flame of a candle is extinguiſhed, and the fire will quickly die out of the ſnuffe: ſo is it in Spiritual caſes; unleſſe we be ſomewhat fervent for truth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, for Church-Ordinances and Diſcipline, we ſhall quickly leave acting for them, and be at a loſſe of them. Therefore <hi>be fervent in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> And to direct our aimes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions in it, know, laſtly, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Scripture) that we muſt look at <hi>the Lords ſervice,</hi> as <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lord,</hi> we muſt be fervent in Spirit, and not ſloathful in buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The Apoſtle bids ordinary
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:154431:59"/> 
               <hi>ſervants</hi> do their Maſters ſervice, not as <hi>looking to them onely, but to the Lord,</hi> (Epheſ. 6. 7. Col. 3. 23.) How much more then ſhould they approve themſelves to the Lord with all fervency of Spirit, whoſe ſervice and buſineſſe is about the matters of God and his houſe! Theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations ſurely may be helpful to Church-Officers and Members to hold faſt what they have.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If we be reſolved for conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in holding faſt what good we have, then let us ſhew our ſelves lovers and obſervers of all good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; Enemies to Order are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Conſtancy; Both together availe much for great iſſues and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements; But pervert or diſturb the former, and you ſubvert or breake the latter: cryers down of all Forms are <hi>[monſtra informia]</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen Monſters, as oppoſite to God in their endeavours as may be; for whereas God brought a bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Creation</hi> out of a Chao's, They
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:154431:59"/> would reduce all into a Chao's again, might they have their will, or wiſhes, for ought appears by their words. Plainly therefore, would we retaine either ſoundneſſe of Doctrine, or holineſſe of life? we muſt pray, and endeavour to keep good order in all Church-Adminiſtrations. Marke that of the Apoſtle in <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>Rejoycing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and beholding your order,</hi> and the <hi>ſtedfaſtneſſe of your faith in Chriſt.</hi> He joynes Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with ſtedfaſtneſſe, and puts Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (though the leſs) before ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of faith, (though the greater) becauſe Order conduceth much unto ſtedfaſtneſs. And wherefore is there ſo much unſtedfaſtneſſe this day among our people, even about the moſt important points of Faith, but becauſe they are all out of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? No Rule held over them, their Traces cut, the Reins caſt upon their necks, and the communalty of them unskilful to rule themſelves; I ſpeak in reference to Spirituals: They
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:154431:60"/> wander from one Church unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, now they are in one Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle or Aſſembly, and then in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; In one place they meet with ſome good Principles (it may be) but in another with bad, and gather matter of corruption of minde, and practice one piece after another, and how then ſhould they hold faſt what good they had? How much then doth it concern us all in our ſeveral places, to keep Order and Rules of Government? And would to God our Rulers at length would power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully help us all to keep ſuch as may be ſound, undoubtedly approve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Exerciſe patience (as this Church did ver. 10. <hi>keeping the word of Chriſts patience,</hi> not only the rule preſcribing patience, but patience it ſelf preſcribed by that rule.) For patience is neceſſary unto perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in a good profeſſion, in a good practice, whether publickly or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately. The impatient perſon doth
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:154431:60"/> not <hi>poſſeſs his own ſoul,</hi> (ſee <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 19.) he hath not an hold faſt of him ſelf, and therefore what elſe can he hold faſt? If we would like good plants retain our moiſture, our ſuſtenance, and <hi>bring forth fruit to perfection, it muſt be with patience,</hi> Luke 8. 15. If we <hi>would do the will of God</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our places) throughly, and conſtantly, ſo as <hi>to receive the promiſes, we have need of patience,</hi> Hebr. 10. 36. Wherefore do ſo many depart from God, and turn from his truth, and will, and way, but becauſe they are impatient, and will not wait Gods leiſure, till he vindicate his own cauſe, or means effectually for the clearing up of Controverſies, and reforming of things amiſs, and ſo falling a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that things are carried croſſe unto their former Principles, and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, they fling out and are carried headily any way that may give them moſt preſent contentment, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it may do afterward. But
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:154431:61"/> not to tire your patience too long:</p>
            <p n="7">7. Approve we our ſelves right <hi>Philadelphians,</hi> that is, (according to the Etymon of the word) <hi>Brotherly lovers,</hi> and lovers of the Brethren. See 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 9. <hi>But as touching brotherly love, ye need not that I write unto you: for ye your ſelves are taught of God to love one another.</hi> Heb. 13. 1. <hi>Let brotherly love continue.</hi> Without this we cannot keep long in any good order: nor keep in patience long, &amp;c. Nor (which is the main) keep long in the poſſeſſion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of truth and holineſs. Mark that Context, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 12, 3. <hi>Forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another in love. Endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</hi> If we break in point of love, we quickly break the bond of peace, and love being broken, we cannot long keep the unity of the Spirit; what is that? Unity in the diſpoſition of our ſpirits, in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and affections: But there muſt be more then that, <hi>viz.</hi> 2. Unity of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:154431:61"/> our ſpirits in aſſent and adherence to Gods Spirit, his Doctrines, his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, his Ordinances; that ſo our unity may be evidenced to be 3. U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiy wrought by the Holy Spirit of God, knitting us together as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one Myſtical body, after a Spiritual and Myſtical manner. To the keeping of this, I ſay, brotherly love is requiſite. No marvel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we hold not faſt what we had, (I ſpeak of the common hold faſt) ſince there is ſuch want of brotherly love among us, ſince our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are fallen into ſo many Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and breaches; A condition with tears of blood to be lamented; And O that all <hi>Sardenſes</hi> and <hi>Laodiceans</hi> about us would <hi>tranſire in caſtra,</hi> or rather <hi>in tentoria Philadelphenſium.</hi> Then might we ſee happy times, and God can bring them on when he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>Mean while, let us Beloved ſhew our ſelves right <hi>Philadelphians,</hi> of an humble, meek, loving, gentle, yet a
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:154431:62"/> couragious, and tenacious ſpirit to hold faſt true Doctrine and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, holineſſe of life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. Our love one toward ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſtrengthen the hearts and hands one of another, and the failing of it as much weaken us, &amp;c. Let Angels, and Officers of Churches think of this in the firſt place, who are to be Lights and Guides to others in the wayes of Love, and Peace: But then all the Members of our Churches in their ſeveral places.</p>
            <p>And (to cloſe all) Let us ſhew our ſelves <hi>Philadelphians</hi> in our ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathetical affections in love towards our Brethren of the reformed Churches beyond the Seas, and of neighbouring Nations, becauſe we all profeſs to hold the ſame good things of God, both for Doctrine and Diſcipline for the main ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it: More ſpecially ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathize with them who are now in an hour of temptation to try them. Pray that though they could not
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:154431:62"/> hold faſt what they had in Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Lands, and other outward poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, nor Miniſters, nor Churches, nor their neareſt relations (many of them) yet they may hold faſt true faith and good conſciences to the end (as many of thoſe that have been maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred already, did to the end) as divers of their Anceſtors alſo did ſee many foregoing Generations; And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute alſo toward them in love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the relief of their neceſſities, as we ſhall be ſhortly called upon to do in our reſpective places.</p>
            <p>Now who ſo in the uſe of ſuch meanes, ſhall hold faſt that which he hath of Truth, and Grace, and perſevering overcome, Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth him in the verſe following, that <hi>he will make him pillar in the Temple of his God, and he ſhall goe no more out.</hi> A verſe very well worthy our attendance unto a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther explanation of it; but the time now cuts me off, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
